Robert Garrett Collection of Ethiopic Magic Scrolls, 1700-1900: Finding Aid C0744.04
Manuscripts Division
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 97, 1770-1830; 97; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a reasonable hand (3-4mm), framed within a linear border with traces of yellow wash. 3 talismanic drawings. (Box 3)
  - Prayer against Sickness Caused by the Evil Eye, circa 1770-1830; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 98, 1830-1870; 98; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together, with a skin thong for tying at the bottom; the scroll is now rolled from the top, part of which has been torn off and is now missing. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a variable and uneven hand (2-5mm), framed within a linear border colored yellow. 3 talismanic drawings. (Box 3)
  Lattice-work knot design. (In ink with yellow color.)
  Ornamented cross. (In ink with yellow color.)
  Knot design. (In ink with yellow color.)
  Owner: Wälättä Negest (f.)
  - Prayer against Aynä T'ela and Qurañña, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for Binding and Anathematizing Satan; Prayer against Aynä S'ela, Qwerañña [sic] and Täyazhi, mid 19th century; 1 item
    Untitled. In continuo.
  - Prayer against Colic; Prayer against Barya, Légéwon, Aynä S'ela and Aynä Wärq, mid 19th century; 1 item
    In continuo. Second prayer is untitled.
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 99, 1830-1870; 99; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in an untidy and compact hand ( framed within a linear border colored yellow. 3 talismanic drawings. (Box 3)
  Cruciform design with a central face and further winged faces at the ends of each lobe-like arm; within the quadrants formed by the arms are additional small "crosses" made of five faces each. (In ink with red, yellow and black color.)
  Guardian angel with drawn sword. (In ink with red and pale yellow color.)
  Owner: Täklä Egzi' (m.)
  - Prayer against Evil and Malevolent Demons, Barya, Légéwon and "All Performers of Evil", mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for Overcoming All One's Enemies and Adversaries, Incorporating a Hymn of Praise to the Trinity, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for Binding Demons and the Evil Eye of Foul and Accursed Barya, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for Undoing Spells, mid 19th century; 1 item
    Classified according to the manner of casting the spell and the regional origin of the caster.
  - Prayer against Colic and Mäggañña, mid 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 100, 1800-1899; 100; 5 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a reasonable hand (3mm), framed within a linear border with traces of yellow wash. 1 talismanic drawing. (Box 3)
  Drawing: Guardian angel with drawn sword. (In ink with possible traces of yellow wash.)
  - Prayer against Sickness Caused by Barya, Légéwon and Zar, 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for Protection from Satan's Snare, Sorcerers and Malevolent Demons, 19th century; 1 item
    Untitled. Contains various stories from the gospel text about healing from possession by spirits.
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 101, 1800-1850; 101; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a somewhat untutored and compact hand (4mm), framed within a linear border colored yellow. 3 talismanic drawings. (Box 3)
  Grid of 15 squares with dotted or transverse cross infill forming a cruciform pattern. (In ink with yellow and some red color.)
  Cross in hand cross form with a figure at the bottom right. (In ink with red and yellow color.) Various pieces of text are written around the figure (mostly in a very untutored hand): the name Wälättä Täklä Haymanot and others that may be the same, but so poorly executed as to be illiterate.
  - Prayer against Barya and Légéwon, Sickness Caused by the Evil Eye and Shotälay, S'elawagi [sic] and Tegrida ... etc, circa 1800-1850; 1 item
  - Prayer and Legend of Susenyos, circa 1800-1850; 1 item
  - Prayer for Binding Demons, circa 1800-1850; 1 item
  - Prayer against Hemorrhage and for Successful Pregnancy, circa 1800-1850; 1 item
  - Prayer against Hemorrhage, circa 1800-1850; 1 item
    Title partly missing.
  - Prayer Known as the Rampart of the Cross (Has'urä Mäsqäl), circa 1800-1850; 1 item
  - Prayer against Colic, circa 1800-1850; 1 item
  - Prayer for Binding Foul Demons 'That Cut the Hearts of Men", circa 1800-1850; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 102, 1830-1870; 102; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in red only in a small, neat hand (2mm), framed within a broad border colored yellow. 3 talismanic drawings. Preserved in a leather cylinder pouch (1 piece). (Box 3)
  Cruciform design with a central face, the whole framed within an oval with eye-motifs in the four quadrants. (In ink with red and yellow color.)
  Cross with central face and stylized faces at the ends of the arms, with winged bird's heads in the four quadrants formed by the arms. (In ink with red and yellow color.)
  Cross with a central face and curving lines connecting the four arms. (In ink with red and yellow color.)
  Owner: Habänä Wäld (m.)
  - A Series of Prayers against Barya and the Evil Eye, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for Banishing Satan, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Terror Caused by Satan, Barya and the Evil Eye, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Terror, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for Binding Satan and Barya and the Evil Eye, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Barya, Zar, Tegrida, Mäggañña, Gusemt ... and Other Malevolent Forces. 7, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Evil Spirits, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against "All Diseases", mid 19th century; 1 item
    Within the text is a talismanic chart in cruciform shape and containing magic letters (harägawi fidäl) and pieces of text written around the central cross. The text additionally contains various purportedly Arabic words for drowning barya and légéwon.
  - Prayer against the Evil Eye and Barya, mid 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 103, 1830-1870; 103; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in an untidy hand (3-4mm), framed within a border with zigzag decoration colored yellow. 3 talismanic drawings. (Box 3)
  Crowned head and shoulders with the flaps of a lämd-cape hanging down. (In ink with red-brown and ochre color.)
  Cruciform shape with central face and bifurcating, curved arms (a cherub ?). (In ink with red and yellow color.)
  Another cruciform shape with a central face and bifurcating, curved arms (a cherub ?). (In ink with red and yellow color.)
  Owner: the original owner's name, Wälättä Abisa Wärqu (f.), has been overwritten by that of Wälättä Abbiyä Egzi'.
  - The Secret Names of Solomon (Asmatä Sälomon), or the Text Known as the Net of Solomon, for Combating Various Spirits and (Here) Diseases; Prayer of Susenyos, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for Undoing Spells (Mäftehé Seray), mid 19th century; 1 item
    The text is followed by a band of magic letters (harägawi fidäl),
  - Prayer against Colic, mid 19th century; 1 item
    Consists mostly of magic syllables and words and includes imprecations against shotolay and qotolay [sic].
  - Prayer against Nädära, mid 19th century; 1 item
    in continuo from preceding text
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 104, 1800-1850; 104; 4 pieces of parchment sewn together. 2 cols., written in black in a small, moderate hand (), framed within a linear border colored yellow and separated by a central margin with rope-like decoration colored red. 4 talismanic drawings. (Box 3)
  Guardian angel with drawn sword. (In ink with red-brown color.)
  [Col. 1] Guardian angel with drawn sword. (In ink with red-brown color.)
  [Col. 2] Eight-pointed star design with central face.
  [Col. 1] Stylized hand cross design with three circles above. At the foot of the scroll are several magical or knotted letters (harägawi fidäl), and a sun and moon motif.
  - Prayer against Sickness Caused by Barya and Légéwon, Zar and Tegrida, Mäggañña and Gusemt ... and Other Malevolent Forces, as Well as against Various Ailments Such as Typhoid and Fever; Prayer For Banishing Barya, etc, circa 1800-1850; 1 item
  - Prayer for Drowning and Confounding Barya and the Binding of Demons, circa 1800-1850; 1 item
    Title lit. "for the disease of drowning and confounding ..." [sic]. The text of the prayer is apparently in Arabic written in Ethiopic script: abuhu bilahiminä säyt'äwani eräjem bäsmilahi ...
  - Prayer against Sickness Caused by Barya and Légéwon, Zar and Tegrida, Mäggañña and Gusemt, circa 1800-1850; 1 item
  - Prayer against Mäst'em (?) and Barya, Demons and Devils, the Evil Eye of Zar and Tegrida, circa 1800-1850; 1 item
  - Prayer against Sickness Caused by Barya and Légéwon, Zar and Tegrida, and Mäggañña, circa 1800-1850; 1 item
  - Prayer against Sickness Caused by Barya and Légéwon, Zar and Tegrida, and Mäggañña, etc, circa 1800-1850; 1 item
    Comprises the prayer and legend of Susenyos.
  - Prayer against Sickness Caused by Barya and Légéwon, Zar and Tegrida, and Mäggañña, etc, circa 1800-1850; 1 item
  - Another Prayer against Sickness Caused by Barya and Légéwon, Zar and Tegrida, and Mäggañña, etc, circa 1800-1850; 1 item
    Contains the text known as the rampart of the Cross [has'urä mäsqäl],
  - Prayer against Terror, circa 1800-1850; 1 item
  - Prayer against Sickness Caused by Barya and Légéwon and Zar, circa 1800-1850; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 105, 1750-1799; 105; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together, the first piece with rodent damage along the edges. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a compact, moderate hand (2mm). 5 well-executed talismanic drawings. (Box 3)
  Seraph (face above crossed wings) and hand cross. (In ink with red, yellow and green color.)
  Regal figure and two attendants. (In ink with red, yellow and green color. Identified by the text above as King Solomon.
  Talismanic diagram comprising a square (in red) containing symbols and surrounded by magical or knotted letters (harägawi fidäl) (also in red).
  Derivative of the eight-pointed star design, comprising a central face within an ornamented and lobed cruciform shape from which four further "wings" extend. (in ink with red, yellow and green color.)
  Guardian angel striking a pair of devils with a drawn sword. (In ink with red, yellow and green color.)
  Owner: the original owner's name, just legible as Wäldä Täklä Haymanot (m.), has been erased and replaced with that of Abnä [sic] Wäld.
  - Prayer for the Binding of Demons and Drowning of Barya and Légéwon, circa 1750-1799; 1 item
  - Prayer for the Binding of Satan, circa 1750-1799; 1 item
  - Prayer for the Drowning of Barya and Demons, circa 1750-1799; 1 item
    The text contains apparently Arabic words and phrases written in Ethiopic script.
  - Prayer against the Evil Eye "Emanating from Red and Black People", circa 1750-1799; 1 item
  - Prayer against (Chest) Pain, circa 1750-1799; 1 item
    Ending with a row of magical letters and stars of David,
  - Prayer for Banishing Any Evil Spirit, Buda or Barya, circa 1750-1799; 1 item
  - Sälam (Hymn of Salutation) to Phanuel, circa 1750-1799; 1 item
  - Prayer against Colic, circa 1750-1799; 1 item
  - Prayer for Undoing Spells "Copied from 88 Books (Mäs'ahe[f]t)", circa 1750-1799; 1 item
  - Prayer for Binding Demons "Spoken by Alexander the King Before Gog And Magog"; Prayer against Colic, Headache, Rheumatism, etc, circa 1750-1799; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 106, 1800-1850; 106; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a moderate hand (3mm). 4 talismanic drawings. (Box 3)
  Eight-pointed star design with central face, the ends of the arms curving back on themselves. (In ink with yellow, pale blue and dark brown color.)
  Another derivative of the eight-pointed star design, or cruciform with bifurcating arms; here the arms of the cross end in faces from the sides of which extend the curved ends of the 'star'. (In ink with yellow, pale blue and reddish brown color.)
  Another eight-pointed star design with a central face; the arms end in eye-motifs. (In ink with yellow, pale blue and reddish brown color.)
  Another eight-pointed star design with a central face constructed within a grid of squares. (In ink with yellow, pale blue and reddish brown color.)
  Owner: the original owner's name has been erased.
  - Prayer or Spell for "Stupefying and Diminishing" One's Enemies; Series of Magic Names (Asmat) "Given by God to Manasseh"; Spell against "Nobles, Princes, Kings, and Bishops Great and Small", circa 1800-1850; 1 item
  - Prayer for Personal Aggrandizement and Favor "Given to David"; Spells for Gaining Power and Influence, circa 1800-1850; 1 item
  - Prayer for Personal Aggrandizement and Favor; Prayer against the Jealousy of Others (?), circa 1800-1850; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 107, circa 1800-1850; 107; 1 box 4 pieces of parchment sewn together, the bottom piece now nearly detached. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a large and untidy hand (5-7mm), framed within a linear border colored yellow. 2 talismanic drawings. 1640 x 65mm (Box 3)
  Guardian angel with drawn sword. (In ink with yellow and reddish brown color.)
  Eight-pointed star design with central face. (In ink with yellow and reddish brown color.)
  The various texts follow one another without separate headings: Prayer against barya and légéwon, incorporating the Prayer and Legend of Susenyos, followed in continuo by another prayer against barya and légéwon; a prayer against hemorrhage; and a sälam (hymn of salutation) to Phanuel.
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 108, 1830-1870; 108; 2 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a mediocre hand (3-7mm). 3 talismanic drawings. (Box 3)
  Grid of 9 squares with alternate face and transverse cross infill. (In ink with red and yellow color.)
  Guardian angel with drawn sword. (In ink with red and yellow color, and set within the text.)
  Derivative of the eight-pointed star design with central face (a cherub ?) with further arms (16 in all), each ending in a circle. (In ink with red and yellow color.)
  Owner: Élsabét' [with added given or baptismal names (?) Wärq Weha or Amätä Sellasé] (f.)
  - Prayer against Shotälay, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer and Legend of Susenyos, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Sälam (Hymn of Salutation) to Phanuel, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Colic, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against (Chest) Pain, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for Undoing Spells (Fethatä Seray), mid 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 109, 1770-1830; 109; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together; the top of the scroll is slightly damaged. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a compact, moderate hand (3mm). 4 finely drawn talismanic drawings. (Box 3)
  Grid of 9 squares, with a figure (head and shoulders) at the centre, faces in the four corner squares, and transverse crosses in the remainder. (In ink with red color, now faded.)
  A central face (a cherub ?) within a rosette-like figure framed within a square with eye-motifs in the four corners. (In ink with red and ochre color.)
  A figure (seated or three-quarters) framed within a derivative of the eight-pointed star design, each "arm" ending in a trefoil, and the whole framed within an oblong. (In ink with red and ochre color.)
  A cruciform design with a central face, the four arms bifurcating and joined (a cherub ?) (In ink with red and ochre color.)
  Owner: S'erha Qeddusan (f.) The names Amätä S'eyon (f.) and Wäldä Mädhen (m.) have been added later in many places.
  - Prayer for Banishing Evil Spirits, circa 1770-1830; 1 item
    Untitled. The text concludes with a grid of 50 squares containing letters,
  - Prayer against Demons, Tegretya [sic], Spells and All Evil Spirits, circa 1770-1830; 1 item
  - Prayer and Legend of Susenyos, circa 1770-1830; 1 item
  - Prayer against Hemorrhage; Prayer for Anathematizing Demons and Binding Evil Spirits, circa 1770-1830; 1 item
  - Prayer against Diseases of the Liver or Stomach; Prayer against Hemorrhage, circa 1770-1830; 1 item
    In continuo. Concluding with a talismanic chart in the form of a grid containing inter alia the names of the Trinity.
  - Prayer for Binding Satan by the Power of the Cross, circa 1770-1830; 1 item
  - Prayer for Binding Barya, Demons, Nägärgar, Buda and Blacksmiths, circa 1770-1830; 1 item
  - Prayer for Protection against Terror, Demons and Foul Légéwon, Barya and Evil Spirits and Evil Men ... etc, circa 1770-1830; 1 item
  - Prayer against Evil Spirits, circa 1770-1830; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 110, 1800-1899; 110; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in an uneven and mediocre hand (3-4mm), framed within a zigzag border with traces of yellow color. 4 roughly executed talismanic drawings. (Box 3)
  Eight-pointed star design with central face. (In ink with traces of red color.)
  Face within a square from which radiate 11 arms ending in circles; the whole is framed within a circle formed of a serpent. (In ink with some red color.)
  Guardian angel (?) with two pairs of wings. (In ink without color.)
  Hand cross. (In ink without color.)
  Owners: Wälättä Kidan, Wälättä Mika'él and Hérutä Mika'él (all f.)
  - Prayer for the Binding of Demons "Spoken by Alexander the King Before Gog and Magog", 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for the Binding of Satan; Prayer against Colic, Headache and Rheumatism, 19th century; 1 item
    In continuo. First prayer contains the story of Jesus' driving out the unclean spirit from a man in the temple.
  - Prayer against Mäggañña and Shotolay [sic], 19th century; 1 item
    Contains the prayer and legend of Susenyos.
  - Prayer against Mäggañña and Shotolay, and for Fertility and a Healthy Pregnancy; Prayer against Headache and Colic, 19th century; 1 item
    Incorporating a grid of 24 squares containing letters.
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 111, 1800-1899; 111; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a reasonable, somewhat large hand (5mm), framed within a linear border colored yellow. 3 talismanic drawings. Preserved in a leather cylinder pouch (2 pieces). Compare scroll no. 57 which appears to have been drawn by the same artist. (Box 3)
  Large figure (220mm) of a guardian angel with drawn sword. (In ink with red, blue and yellow wash.)
  A pair of angels either side of a double hand cross. (In ink with red, blue and yellow wash.)
  Large figure (220mm) of a guardian angel with a drawn sword. (In ink with red, blue and yellow wash.)
  Owner: Wälättä Sellasé (f.)
  - Prayer for Binding Zar, Tegrida and Buda, Algum, Dedeq and the Noontide Demon, "Spoken by Alexander the King Before Gog and Magog on Friday", 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for Banishing Evil Spirits, 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for Drowning Demons and Devils, Barya and Légéwon, 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for Drowning Demons and Devils, 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 112, 1830-1870; 112; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a mediocre hand (3-4mm). 4 talismanic drawings. (Box 3)
  Eight-point star design with central face constructed within a grid pattern, containing numerous eye-motifs. (In ink with red and ochre color.)
  Grid of 12 squares with a central face and alternating transverse cross and eye-motifs in the remainder. (In ink with red and ochre color.)
  Eight-pointed star design with central face (a cherub ?). (In ink with red and ochre color.)
  Hand cross with two seraphim either side. (In ink with red and ochre color.)
  - Prayer for Banishing Evil Spirits; Prayer for Banishing Satan, Barya, Demons, Légéwon, Degretya [sic] And Nägärgar, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for Abjuring Satan, Demons of the Air, the "King of Nuba," Demons of the Sea .... etc.; Prayers against All Evil Spirits, Barya, Däsk, Gudalé, Blacksmiths, Mäggañña, Gwesemt, T'äfänt, etc, as Well as Various Ailments, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Demons, mid 19th century; 1 item
    Contains the secret names of Solomon [asmatä Sälomon].
  - Prayer against Blacksmiths; Prayer Against Malevolent Demons, mid 19th century; 1 item
    In continuo. Second prayer contains the opening of the Gospel of John.
  - Prayer against Barya and Shotolay [sic], mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Barya "Which Breaks the Bones and Strangles the Neck"; Prayer against the Enemy, mid 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 113, 1830-1870; 113; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. 2 cols, written in black with rubrics in a poor and cramped hand (3-4mm), separated by an uncolored linear central margin. 3 roughly executed talismanic drawings. (Box 3)
  2 regal figures (?) side by side, separated by a continuation of the central margin of the text. (In ink with dark reddish brown and ochre color.)
  Grid of 9 squares with alternating face and transverse cross infill, and a face above and below the grid. (In ink with reddish brown and ochre color.)
  2 figures with raised hands, again separated by a continuation of the central margin of the text. (In ink with reddish brown and ochre color.)
  Owner: Wälättä S'eyon (f.)
  - Prayer and Legend of Susenyos, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for Blood Clotting (Arge'a Däm) and against Miscarriage, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for Banishing Demons, mid 19th century; 1 item
    Comprises the secret names of Solomon [asmatä Sälomon] or Net of Solomon.
  - Prayer against Hemorrhage; Prayer for Fertility and Successful Pregnancy; Prayer for Binding Demons "Spoken by Alexander the King Before Gog and Magog"; Prayer against Colic, mid 19th century; 1 item
    In continuo. Untitled. First prayer contains the Story of the woman with an issue of blood.
  - Prayer against (Chest) Pain; Prayers Against Colic and Hemorrhage, mid 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 114, mid 19th century; 114; 1 box Tapering to 30mm at the bottom. 4 pieces of vellum sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a large and angular hand (5-6mm). 3 talismanic drawings. 1620 x 50-55mm (Box 3)
  Prayer against sickness caused by demons, barya, shotolay [sic], and tegretya [sic]; prayer for blood clotting and against hemorrhage. Contains the prayer and legend of Susenyos.
  Head and shoulders of an angel above a grid of 9 squares filled with transverse cross and eye-motif designs. (In ink with red and yellow color.)
  Hand cross with sun and moon. (In ink with red and yellow color.)
  Owner: the original owner's name, Eléni Mesraqawit (?) (f.), has been erased and replaced with that of Wälättä Täklä Haymanot (f.)
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 115, 19th century; 115; 1 box Tapering to 65mm at the bottom. 2 pieces of parchment sewn together, forming the bottom part of a scroll, the top piece now missing. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a moderate and open hand (4-5mm). 1 talismanic drawing. 1120 x 75-80mm (Box 3)
  Prayer for the Undoing of Spells, "Which Came Out of Jerusalem" [incomplete]. Containing inter alia sections on each of the letters of the Hebrew alphabet.
  Drawing: 2 figures, one female, seated and holding an infant. (In ink with some reddish brown color.) There is a small sketch (in ink) of a hand cross at the bottom of the scroll.
  Owner: [Berch'eqo] Wälättä S'eyon (f.)